Finding Aid for Church of the Ascension, Detroit, Mich., Records 1911-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Church of the Ascension, Detroit, Mich., records 1911-1988
Church of the Ascension (Detroit, Mich.)
Episcopal church located in Detroit, Michigan; church records include church histories, vestry minutes, annual parish meeting minutes and reports, membership directories and card indexes, scattered correspondence and bulletins, records of church women's organization, and photographs.; also register of baptisms, marriages, burials, and communicants; and registers of church services.
967 Ba 2 UBAm
3 linear feet
5 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was deposited by the Michigan Diocese of the Episcopal Church (donor no. 1059 ) and came to the library in 1995 and 2002.
The record group is open for research.
The Church of the Ascension, an Episcopal church located in Detroit, Michigan, began as a parochial mission of St. Thomas' Church in 1905. The following year, the future parish was organized as a diocesan mission with the Reverend Henry E. Ridley as priest-in-charge. In 1912, Rev. John B. Ashlee began services in the basement of a church building still under construction. After merging with St. Mark's in 1922, "Ascension" was admitted to the Episcopal Diocese as a parish. The first annual parish meeting was held in the newly dedicated building on February 24, 1922. The church was consecrated on December 20, 1942. The parish prospered throughout the middle of the century, offering a variety of programs for almsgiving, outreach, and music, as well as sponsoring youth and women's organizations.
In the late 1970s, Ascension began to experience a decline in membership due to changes in the community. In 1983, upon recommendation of the diocese, Ascension initiated a Hispanic Outreach Program. On June 18, 1983, the Rev. Gene E. Curry celebrated the first Spanish language service before a congregation of fifteen. In its last decade, Ascension quickly evolved into a Spanish-speaking parish. In 1984, the church instituted a Reachout Program to assist the children of the church and their immigrant parents; the parish now included many Mexicans, Puerto Ricans, Peruvians, and Panamanians. Mr. Karl N. Laubenstein, who worked with the parish first as a layman and later as priest, was largely responsible for the revival of the parish. From September 1986 to the closing of the church, the Rev. Efrain 'Jeffrey' Gonzalez led the parish as Rector, emphasizing evangelism, stewardship, and church growth. Ascension, probably for financial reasons, ceased operation sometime in the late 1980's.
The records of the Church of the Ascension Church span most of this parish's history, though there are many gaps especially in the late 1970s through to its demise in the 1980s. The record group is strongest for the middle period of the church's history. There is unfortunately little material relating to the ethnic changeover of the church in its last decade. The record group has been arranged into the following series: Registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants; Registers of church services; Historical/background information; Vestry meeting minutes; Parish meetings/reports; Church Office; and Church organizations. The Historical/Background Information series includes written histories, newspaper clippings, and photographs of church personalities and activities. The greatest depth of information about the church is found in the run of Vestry meeting minutes and the series of Parish meetings/reports.
Subjects:
Church of the Ascension (Detroit, Mich.); Church buildings--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Church history.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Detroit.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Church of the Ascension (Detroit, Mich.); Churches--Michigan--Detroit.; Detroit (Mich.)--Churches.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Registers of baptisms, burials, marriages, communicants
  - Comprehensive volumes
    - 1911-1923 (Volume 1)
      (marriages to 1916 only)
    - 1912-1926 (Volume 2)
    - 1927-1946 (Volume 3)
  - Marriage register 1926-1940 (Box 1)
  - Marriage register 1940-1947 (Box 1)
  - Marriage register 1947-1991 (Volume 4)
  - Register of communicants 1951-1971 (scattered) (Box 1)
    (volume no. 5)
  - Register of confirmations 1942-1992 (Box 1)
  - Register of burials 1947-1988 (Box 1)
  - Register of baptisms 1947-1971 (Box 1)
  - Register of baptisms 1971-1988 (Box 1)
- Registers of church services
  - 1955-1977, 2 volumes (Box 1)
- Historical/background information
  - Written histories; include "The history of the Episcopal Church of the Ascension, Detroit, Michigan, 1896-1976" by John O. Tooroian and "Annals of Our Parish' 1960 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper clippings 1938-1974 (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Church rectors, church groups, etc. (Box 2)
    - Rector Garfield Brown and church groups, 3 items (Folder UBAm)
- Vestry meeting minutes 1922-1974
  - February 1922-January 1928 (Box 2)
    (includes annual parish meeting reports for 1922-1928)
  - January 1928-January 1939 (bound) (Box 2)
  - September 1935-January 1945 (Box 2)
  - 1951, December 1954-December 1959 (Box 2)
  - January 1965-January 1974 (Box 2)
- Parish meetings/reports
  - Annual parish meeting reports 1924-1988 (incomplete), 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Parochial reports 1945-1987 (Box 2)
- Church Office
  - Bulletins (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1915-1988 (Box 2)
  - Membership directories 1975, 1986- (Box 3)
  - Membership cards (Box 3)
    (2 sets of index cards located at the end of box 2)
- Church organizations
  - Choir/organ information (Box 3)
  - Episcopal Church Women 1966-1980 (Box 3)
  - St. Mary's Altar Guild 1956-1985 (Box 3)
  - Women's Auxiliary 1937-1941 (Box 3)
  - Women's Guild 1924-1929 (Box 3)